<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Wintermute Dev Logs</title><link href="http://ajoo.blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://ajoo.blog/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://ajoo.blog/</id><updated>2016-12-18T12:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Software Defined GNSS</title><link href="http://ajoo.blog/software-defined-gnss.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-18T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-12-18T12:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Ajoo</name></author><id>tag:ajoo.blog,2016-12-18:/software-defined-gnss.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short introduction to my Software Defined &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNSS&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;project&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I first heard about Software Defined Radios (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SDR&lt;/span&gt;) I was instantly interested. The ability to probe the electromagnetic spectrum around me and decode the ubiquitous signals being transmitted seemed to open a door to new and interesting experiments. I loved Digital Signal Processing (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DSP&lt;/span&gt;) when I was in college (still do) and this was exactly what I was looking for to put it in practice. I started looking for a project to sink my teeth in that went besides using established software and a cheap &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SDR&lt;/span&gt; to decode well known &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AM&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FM&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ADS&lt;/span&gt;-B&amp;nbsp;signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since my main background is in Guidance, Navigation and Control (and I&amp;#8217;m a person walking this Earth in 2016) I&amp;#8217;ve made use of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; before and I&amp;#8217;m familiar to some extent with its inner workings from a course in Global Navigation Satellite Systems (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNSS&lt;/span&gt;) I attended in college. I&amp;#8217;ve always felt however that my knowledge of this system is not as deep as I want it to be, particularly regarding the receiver side of things. I think it&amp;#8217;s therefore appropriate that my first foray into the exciting world of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SDR&lt;/span&gt; be the implementation of a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNSS&lt;/span&gt; receiver in software. I intend to take this as far as I can, from measuring &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; L1 signals to computing a full navigation solution of position and velocity, learning as much as I can along the way and sharing it with any interested&amp;nbsp;readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My particular goals for this project are&amp;nbsp;therefore:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To put my knowledge of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNSS&lt;/span&gt;, telecommunications and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DSP&lt;/span&gt; to work in a practical setting and keep me from getting&amp;nbsp;rusty;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To fill in the blanks in my knowledge of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNSS&lt;/span&gt; receivers&amp;#8217; inner&amp;nbsp;workings;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To learn about new software libraries and tools, in particular those concerning real time digital signal&amp;nbsp;processing;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To improve my communication and documentation&amp;nbsp;skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Materials&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are only two components (three if you&amp;#8217;re counting a decent computer/laptop) required for this project. One is an active &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; Antenna in order to be able to receive &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; signals in the L1 band (1575.42 MHz center frequency) and the other is a Software Defined Radio (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SDR&lt;/span&gt;) which is responsible for delivering to your computer the digital samples of these signals shifted to&amp;nbsp;baseband.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will go into further detail into the hardware in my next blog post so don&amp;#8217;t worry if you don&amp;#8217;t understand what this is for just yet. This section is only meant to give you an idea of what you&amp;#8217;ll need and the costs associated. The particular choices I made&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/RTL-SDR-Blog-RTL2832U-Software-Telescopic/dp/B011HVUEME/ref=lp_10230687011_1_1?srs=10230687011&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1482078660&amp;amp;sr=8-1"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RTL&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SDR&lt;/span&gt; Blog &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; Dongle&lt;/a&gt; ($26) I chose this over other generic &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DVB&lt;/span&gt;-T &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; dongles because it has a software enabled bias-T which allows me to power an active antenna without additional hardware or soldering mods. It also has other nice enhancements over regular dongles for use in Software Defined Radio. You could also get the version without the antennas which comes out cheaper ($20) since we&amp;#8217;re mostly interested in using a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;antenna.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Waterproof-Active-Antenna-28dB-Gain/dp/B00LXRQY9A/ref=lp_10008493011_1_1?srs=10008493011&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1482079461&amp;amp;sr=8-1"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; Active Antenna&lt;/a&gt; ($15) Any active &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; antenna should do, there are plenty available at Amazon and other specialized&amp;nbsp;sellers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a picture I took of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; dongle and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; antenna with a 2 Euro coin for&amp;nbsp;scale:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="RTL Dongle and GPS Antenna" src="http://ajoo.blog/images/Rtl_Dongle_and_GPS_Antenna.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Existing Software Libraries and Target Audience for These Blog&amp;nbsp;Posts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software based &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNSS&lt;/span&gt; receivers are hardly uncharted waters. There are full fledged software libraries meant to accomplish what this little project of mine set out to do. Below is a list of those I&amp;#8217;m aware&amp;nbsp;of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/taroz/GNSS-SDRLIB"&gt;gnss-sdrlib&lt;/a&gt; An open source &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNSS&lt;/span&gt; Software Defined Radio Library with nice &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt; elements written in C and&amp;nbsp;C++&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://gnss-sdr.org"&gt;gnss-sdr&lt;/a&gt; An open source library for implementing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNSS&lt;/span&gt; software defined receivers in&amp;nbsp;C++&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.rtklib.com/"&gt;rtklib&lt;/a&gt; An open source program package for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNSS&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;positioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will not rely on these libraries except maybe for inspiration and test purposes as this project is meant mostly as an educational experience for myself and for any readers out there. I will attempt to make my posts as informative and as self-contained as possible so that I can refer back to them in the future and so that any reader might follow along and understand how to decode &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNSS&lt;/span&gt; signals without having to refer to external materials. I will assume only basic knowledge of telecommunications, specially regarding the use of Fourier transforms and time &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; frequency representation of signals but no previous knowledge of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNSS&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Up&amp;nbsp;Next&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next post in this series will go into detail into what exactly is Software Defined Radio and the particular hardware and software that will be used in this project. Stay&amp;nbsp;tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Useful&amp;nbsp;Links:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://sdrgps.blogspot.com"&gt;sdrgps blog&lt;/a&gt; A blog by Philip Hahn on his experiments with software defined radio &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; and its use in high-power&amp;nbsp;rockets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="GNSS"></category><category term="RTL-SDR"></category></entry><entry><title>First Post</title><link href="http://ajoo.blog/first-post.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-17T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-12-17T14:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Ajoo</name></author><id>tag:ajoo.blog,2016-12-17:/first-post.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Season&amp;#8217;s greetings! I&amp;#8217;ve decided to get an early start on my New Years resolution of writing a personal blog. It&amp;#8217;s been on my bucket list for a long time and I&amp;#8217;m glad that it is finally coming to fruition. In this blog I hope to document …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Season&amp;#8217;s greetings! I&amp;#8217;ve decided to get an early start on my New Years resolution of writing a personal blog. It&amp;#8217;s been on my bucket list for a long time and I&amp;#8217;m glad that it is finally coming to fruition. In this blog I hope to document my personal projects and in turn find the motivation to work on them more assiduously. I often find myself talking about them with an imaginary audience, explaining my small decisions and boasting about my small successes, and this looks like a healthier and more useful application of my impulse to share and&amp;nbsp;educate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides my personal projects, I&amp;#8217;m an avid learner and often succumb to reading textbooks on topics I find interesting. I will also try to share some of what I learn and have learned in the past, both as a way to organize my thoughts, to refresh my knowledge on certain topics and to have a place to refer back to when I need it. I&amp;#8217;ll strive to keep these interesting for any reader but I can&amp;#8217;t promise&amp;nbsp;anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as my interests go, and what to expect from this blog, I&amp;#8217;d say if you&amp;#8217;re technology oriented I hope I have something to offer you. My background is mostly in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guidance%2C_navigation%2C_and_control"&gt;Guidance, Navigation and Control&lt;/a&gt; and in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/System_identification"&gt;System Identification&lt;/a&gt; and I hope to be able to make use of this extensively in future projects and perhaps more theoretical posts. While my degree is in Aerospace Engineering I am also very interested in robotics in general and I&amp;#8217;d love to get to build a few fun things in the near future. Finally, I&amp;#8217;m an adept participant in machine learning challenges (&lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com"&gt;kaggle&lt;/a&gt; mostly) and I love statistics. One of my main motivations for starting this blog was being able to do post-mortems of my participations and share what I&amp;#8217;ve learn during each&amp;nbsp;competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the immediate future I will be starting a project to get acquainted with Software Defined Radio by implementing a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; receiver in software. I also want to participate in one or more of the following ongoing kaggle competitions: &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/c/two-sigma-financial-modeling"&gt;Two Sigma Financial Modeling Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/c/dstl-satellite-imagery-feature-detection"&gt;Dstl Satellite Imagery Feature Detection&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/c/the-nature-conservancy-fisheries-monitoring"&gt;The Nature Conservancy Fisheries Monitoring&lt;/a&gt; so you can expect a post-mortem in a couple month&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s it for now. Thanks for reading and I hope I&amp;#8217;ve piqued your&amp;nbsp;interest&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>