<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Ajoo's Blog - General</title><link href="http://ajoo.blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://ajoo.blog/feeds/general.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://ajoo.blog/</id><updated>2016-12-17T14:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>First Post</title><link href="http://ajoo.blog/first-post.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-17T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-12-17T14:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Ajoo</name></author><id>tag:ajoo.blog,2016-12-17:/first-post.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Season&amp;#8217;s greetings! I&amp;#8217;ve decided to get an early start on my New Years resolution of writing a personal blog. It&amp;#8217;s been on my bucket list for a long time and I&amp;#8217;m glad that it is finally coming to fruition. In this blog I hope to document …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Season&amp;#8217;s greetings! I&amp;#8217;ve decided to get an early start on my New Years resolution of writing a personal blog. It&amp;#8217;s been on my bucket list for a long time and I&amp;#8217;m glad that it is finally coming to fruition. In this blog I hope to document my personal projects and in turn find the motivation to work on them more assiduously. I often find myself talking about them with an imaginary audience, explaining my small decisions and boasting about my small successes, and this looks like a healthier and more useful application of my impulse to share and&amp;nbsp;educate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides my personal projects, I&amp;#8217;m an avid learner and often succumb to reading textbooks on topics I find interesting. I will also try to share some of what I learn and have learned in the past, both as a way to organize my thoughts, to refresh my knowledge on certain topics and to have a place to refer back to when I need it. I&amp;#8217;ll strive to keep these interesting for any reader but I can&amp;#8217;t promise&amp;nbsp;anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as my interests go, and what to expect from this blog, I&amp;#8217;d say if you&amp;#8217;re technology oriented I hope I have something to offer you. My background is mostly in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guidance%2C_navigation%2C_and_control"&gt;Guidance, Navigation and Control&lt;/a&gt; and in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/System_identification"&gt;System Identification&lt;/a&gt; and I hope to be able to make use of this extensively in future projects and perhaps more theoretical posts. While my degree is in Aerospace Engineering I am also very interested in robotics in general and I&amp;#8217;d love to get to build a few fun things in the near future. Finally, I&amp;#8217;m an adept participant in machine learning challenges (&lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com"&gt;kaggle&lt;/a&gt; mostly) and I love statistics. One of my main motivations for starting this blog was being able to do post-mortems of my participations and share what I&amp;#8217;ve learned during each&amp;nbsp;competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the immediate future I will be starting a project to get acquainted with Software Defined Radio by implementing a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; receiver in software. I also want to participate in one or more of the following ongoing kaggle competitions: &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/c/two-sigma-financial-modeling"&gt;Two Sigma Financial Modeling Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/c/dstl-satellite-imagery-feature-detection"&gt;Dstl Satellite Imagery Feature Detection&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/c/the-nature-conservancy-fisheries-monitoring"&gt;The Nature Conservancy Fisheries Monitoring&lt;/a&gt; so you can expect a post-mortem in a couple month&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s it for now. Thanks for reading and I hope I&amp;#8217;ve piqued your&amp;nbsp;interest&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>